<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A general epistle to friends every where Written in obedience to the requirings of the spirit of life from God.</title>
            <author>Parke, James, 1636-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56022</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P371</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218729</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830300</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830300</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34750</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56022)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34750)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1874:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A general epistle to friends every where Written in obedience to the requirings of the spirit of life from God.</title>
                  <author>Parke, James, 1636-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Alton in Hampshire .. the end of the 11th mon. 1682 .. James Parke.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bevan-Niash Collection, Woodbrooke College, Birmingham, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34750:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A General Epiſtle</hi> TO FRIENDS Every Where. Written in obedience to the Requirings of the Spirit of Life from God.</head>
            <argument>
               <head>Some of the things ſpoken to in this Epiſtle.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>GOd's peculiar Love and Favour manifeſted to the People of God; With a Salutation to them.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The manner of Gods bringing of us out of ſpiritual</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Aegypt, <hi>and his end therein.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Something of the old Serpents ſubtilty and cunning working; with a way opened for all (how to eſcape it) that are convinced of the Truth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Some wholſom Exhortations unto all who are come to the Way of God, to continue ſtedfaſt in it, and to be conſtant in their Obedience to Chriſt Jeſus unto the end. With ſomething by way of Advice, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the Whores Cup, and that ye receive not the Beaſts Mark on your Foreheads, or in your Hands. Alſo, concerning mighty things done by Faith. A few words concerning Marriage: And ſeveral other things relating to Huſbands and Wives, Parents and Children, Maſters and Servants.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A friendly Caution to all ſuch who have tranſported, or may tranſport themſelves beyond the Seas into forreign Plantations.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </argument>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends and Brethren;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHO are the called of God in Chriſt Jeſus, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the hope of your calling out of Darkneſs into his marvellous Light, and are the Children of the Light and of the Day, The dear and tender Salutation of my Love, in the Light, Life and Spirit of God, reacheth to you all,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34750:2"/>with freſh and fervent deſires, that you all may be kept faithful unto him who hath called, and alſo made choice of you to ſerve, worſhip, love and obey him in your generation, that you may be called the Trees of Righteouſneſs, of the Lords planting, his Seed taking deep Root in you, you will all bring forth fruit to the honour and glory of him who hath not only planted, but often alſo watred you with his heavenly dew &amp; ſhowers of plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Rain, which purely and refreſhingly hath fallen down upon you, as no People elſe hath witneſſed the like in our age or gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, nor hath been known ſince the Apoſtles days, glory to the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, he hath made many Trees fruitful, that now remain as lively, freſh and green as ever, altho ſome are not only withered, but dead twice and pluckt up by the Root, that were planted, and have been watred with us often by our heavenly Father, the Husband man both to us and them, who did ſow the ſame good Seed in them Grounds that prove evil, as on that which is good Ground; and that which he plants or ſows in any mans heart is good, and ſhews man what is purely good, and of God, from that which is contrary, that all might come to love the good, and hate the evil, as its manifeſt from God by his immortal Seed or Word of Life within, and that all might chuſe the good and refuſe the evil, as either appear, or is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to any particular; all are to love the good, and hate the evil; to chuſe the good, and refuſe the evil; to joyn to, and be one with the good, but to ſeparate from, reject and deny that which is evil; and the pure Light of Chriſt in every Conſcience (as all take heed thereunto, and wait therein) will let them ſee, and know how to diſtinguiſh betwixt good and evil, under what diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, fair pretence or transformation of the Enemy ſoever it may appear, to blind, beguile or deceive the ſimple, either to keep in the evil always from the good, or to lead out and draw from the good, after taſtes of it, into the evil again, to make the latter end of ſuch worſe than their beginning. I ſay, and teſtifie in the Lord, <hi>dear Friends,</hi> as we all keep in, and mind the glorious Light of the Son of God, no ſuch Darkneſs will ever again come over any of us, as to call <hi>good evil,</hi> or <hi>evil good,</hi> to put <hi>light</hi> for <hi>darkneſs,</hi> and <hi>darkneſs</hi> for <hi>light, ſweet</hi> for <hi>bitter,</hi> or <hi>bitter</hi> for <hi>ſweet;</hi> for that cometh of Darkneſs, from the Prince of Darkneſs, and God of this World; even the blindneſs that ſome are in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34750:2"/>who profeſs the <hi>light,</hi> yet put <hi>darkneſs</hi> for it, and call <hi>good evil,</hi> and <hi>evil good;</hi> and how can ſuch know the good and acceptable will of God, or good from evil? then they were not like to chuſe the good, and refuſe the evil: And how were they like to obey the Light of Chriſt, or walk in it, that cannot clearly or truly diſtinguiſh betwixt <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs, Chriſt</hi> or <hi>Belial!</hi> May not ſuch follow <hi>darkneſs</hi> in ſtead of <hi>light,</hi> and <hi>Belial</hi> inſtead of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> nay, do they not walk in <hi>darkneſs,</hi> not knowing whither they walk, whoſe Minds thus are blinded by <hi>darkneſs?</hi> And ſuch, to the <hi>Children of the Light,</hi> and of the <hi>Day,</hi> may be known by this Character, that though they profeſs the Light of Chriſt, and have been convinced by it, yet they hate it, and will not bring their deeds to it, to be proved and tryed; this Prover and Tryer that judgeth and condemns for ſin and evil they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide the coming of, but would have their works and things tryed and proved by the Darkneſs which they themſelves are in. Which, <hi>dear Friends,</hi> I tenderly beſeech you in the love of God to beware of, and dwell in the Light of the Son of God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, mind it, love and believe in it as much as ever you did ſince you turned to it, and came to believe in it, then I know you will be as willing to bring your deeds to it as ever you were, and will be as ready to imbrace and follow the motions of it, as you were at your firſt Convincement, or the Candle of the Lord firſt ſhined upon your Tabernacles: And I doubt not but a Remnant are ſo at this day, although ſome are already turned aſide from the Light into great Darkneſs, and loſt the ſence of Life, having Death over them, and they feed thereon, being out of the green and freſh Paſtures of Life, where once they fed with us gladly, and accounted them good and precious, which now ſeems but to them as the Manna did to the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they had eaten thereof and were full, how did many of them forget the Lord and his works, and murmured againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> that was faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in God's houſe, and ſaid, <hi>Hath he brought us hither to deſtroy us?</hi> And they ſaid, <hi>Can God furniſh a Table in the Wilderneſs?</hi> which was alſo a queſtioning of Gods Power and Providence; All which were the fruits and evil effects of Unbelief, and their revolting and ackſliding Hearts; and the Lord ſaid, <hi>Iſrael hath caſt off the thing that is good;</hi> he ſaw it, was angry and greatly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34750:3"/>diſpleaſed therewith; and the Lord did forſake them, and caſt them off, becauſe they did forſake him, and caſt off the thing that was good, and followed after that which evil, and often did evil in the ſight of the Lord; and many ways God proved them, and tryed them, and did mighty things for them, for his Names ſake, and for <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſake he cut <hi>Rahab,</hi> &amp; wounded the Dragon, &amp; divid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and made a way in the Sea, a good and ſafe Paſſage for them in the Journey which the Lord led them on in; he carried them on Eagles Wings, and rebuked Kings, and ſubdued ſtrong Nations before them; but when they rebelled, then he turned to be their Enemy, and fought againſt them whom he had often ſaved, and had been afflicted with them in their Afflictions.</p>
            <p>So, <hi>dear Friends,</hi> you that are gathered to God by his gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Arm of Love and Power, keep with the Lord, and forſake him not whatſoever you may ſuffer for his Names ſake therein; the Lord will appear to your joy, and will afflict them that afflict you for your obedience to God, and the keeping your Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces pure and good in his ſight: Let not a revolting or rebellious Heart be found in any one of you, ſuch cannot continue or abide with the Lord whoſe hearts are evil and rebellious, out of them cometh not good things, their hearts are defiled with evil, filled with it, and bent to do wickedly, and they cannot ceaſe from ſin. And how hath the Devil loaded ſome with Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, that do yet profeſs the ſame Light and Way of God with us? How do they manifeſtly appear Children that are corrupters or corrupt Children, endeavouring to corrupt the Minds of the Profeſſors, and other People, by the ſeeds of Corruption which they have ſown and printed for them to feed upon; and its the evil Seeds-man that ſows corrupt or evil Seed: What Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſoever are by him made uſe of in that work, mark them, and avoid them as Inſtruments of Unrighteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>Friends!</hi> as you love your eternal Reſt and Peace with God, watch againſt, and ſhut out the ſeed of the Serpent, and his evil Seeds-men that ſow it abroad; by the Light of the Lord which ſhines in your hearts (and hath given you the knowledge of God) you may diſcern and ſee clearly the old Serpent's cunning in his Agents, what high ſwelling words ſoever, in their vain minds they may come with amongſt you, or print for Food to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34750:3"/>and the unclean. Be ye ſtedfaſt, always abounding in the work of the Lord, unto which you are called of God; be not beguiled any one of you by the Serpent's cunning; wait low in the pure Simplicity, and that will give knowledge and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the wiles and cunning working of the creeping Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. And now is the ſeed of God riſen to break the head of the Serpent, and to tread under foot his power and authority, which he hath got in man and women by diſobedience, and their rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt God, whereby man in the beginning was ſubjected to vanity, and not willing, but by a ſalfe hope the Devil had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in them, which was the cauſe of their being beguiled, the begetting of that falſe hope, <hi>that they ſhould be as Gods, knowing good and evil,</hi> and as if they ſhould not dye, notwitſtanding their tranſgreſſing the Command of the Lord, which the Serpent's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful and beguiling Doctrine ſubjected them into the belief of. Therefore take heed that none of you be beguiled as the Serpent beguiled <hi>Eve,</hi> and draw you from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt Jeſus. It ſeems the Believers which the Apoſtle writ to had a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſimplicity and ſtedfaſtneſs in the Truth of God, but afterward were in ſome danger to be drawn from it; but <hi>Eve</hi> had not been ſo beguiled if ſhe had minded to keep Gods command &amp; counſel, and not hearkned to the Serpent. So hearken not to the doctrine or voice of the Serpent, which leads from God, into Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and to death, from the Life of God, and to loſe the Image of God, which <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> were deprived of, though once beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified therewith: And ſo Gods Image may be loſt now by them that are come into it, and have born it, and the beauty of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that any one had, may be loſt, if there be not a keeping in that Power which brings into it, and preſerves the faithful in it. The heavenly Creator in the new Creation, createth us in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, and he reſtores his People to God in his Image, which is after God in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs; ſo we become holy as the Lord our God is holy, and perfect as our heavenly Father is Perfect; and ſo we are <hi>a choſen Generation and a royal Prieſthood to God,</hi> and are prepared of him to offer an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering acceptable and well-pleaſing in the ſight of God, and come to know how to pleaſe God in all things, and to hearken to his voice, and obey his Voice, that is better than Sacrifice or the ſat
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34750:4"/>of Rams, which ſome content themſelves with, even a bare Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Truth and Knowledge of, but do not obey it nor walk in it, but rather cauſe the way of Truth to be evil ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, opening the Mouthes of Adverſaries to blaſpheme that holy Name by which we were called, and who know the Truth, but act contrary to the guidance of that Spirit of Truth which led them into the Truth, and the Way wherein they ſhould go, and ſo go into the Apoſtacy, and to turn back again into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> which all ought to beware of; for we were not brought out of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy or delivered out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> either to look, back or go back again. Did not the Lord by a very mighty hand, &amp; ſtretched out Arm bring us out of <hi>Egypt</hi> ſpiritually, as really as he did the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of outward <hi>Egypt</hi> in the days of old? And how did God wound and overthrow our Enemies (though ſtrong and potent) not by any might or power carnal, but by his own holy Spirit and Power, which he made known in our hearts, and which we received from him? Hath not this conquered and overcome many of your Enemies that oppreſſed you, which you groaned under, and were ſorrowful becauſe of, till deliverance came? And cannot many of you ſay, that the right hand of the Lord hath brought mighty things to paſs, and that the right hand of the Lord hath done valiantly? And cannot you ſay, the Lord was on your ſide, and now is the ſame; and that greater is he that is in you than he that is in the World? Although, <hi>dear Friends,</hi> you have many Enemies yet to encounter with, fear not, neither be at all diſmayed, only look to the Lord, and believe in him, and love and truſt in him; fear not man, nor put no truſt in Princes, nor in any Arm of fleſh; and if the wicked bend their Bow, and ſhoot their Arrows at you who are innocent in your Minds, and of a peaceable Life, matter it not, but look to the Lord, that Innocency and a peaceable Mind ſtill may be found in you all; leave your cauſe to the Lord to plead, who in his own due time will plead your cauſe, &amp; execute judgment for you; the Lord can if he pleaſe, ſoon break the Bow of the Wicked, and turn their Arrows againſt themſelves, and make all their Weapons they form againſt you, unproſperous, and cut off their expectation that ſeek your Ruin and Deſtruction: And as Innocency is found in you, and you preſerved in a godly and peaceable life, you will
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34750:4"/>never envy them that oppreſs you, nor chuſe any of their ways, but will mind Gods good old <hi>Way, Truth</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> and will not walk in the way of the Wicked Ungodly men, nor ſit in the ſeat of the Scornful, Proud and Arogant, which leads to Death and Deſtruction; if you ſee many in that way, let not that be an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for you to ſtumble at, or to forſake the way of the Lord, which is narrow, and leads to Life, Peace and Reſt that is Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, wherein you have learned to truſt in the Lord, &amp; to ſtand reſign'd up to his will in the moſt perilous times, when they come; and wherein you have learned to love the Lord and one another with that <hi>love</hi> which is ſhed abroad from <hi>God</hi> in your hearts, and is unfeigned, in which <hi>dear Friends</hi> forever dwell; and ſhut out all Deceit, Hypocriſie and Diſſimulation, which doth render them black amongſt us that have not put away, or are not purged from ſuch things, and ſo doth Envy, Wrath or Malice where-ever it is, which is all for the fire, and to be purged away, that you may pray in the Spirit of the living God, by which you were all quickened; quench it not, neither grieve it, nor rebel againſt it; for that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the heavenly joy and comforts of the Spirit, when Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ariſeth becauſe of the Word. Let not any of you be found without true joy and comfort, when you may have need enough of it, and behold many weeping and wailing for want of it; for certainly it will be woful and miſerable for that man or woman that is without the comfort and joy of the holy Spirit, when no comfort and laſting joy will be found in any viſible created thing, which this World can afford; mens hearts already begin to be aſtoniſhed, and to fail them for fear, becauſe of the things that are coming to paſs; for not only the Powers of the Earth, but the Powers of the Heavens ſhall be ſhaken.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friends,</hi> let not any of you be found an evil or ſloathful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, that ſhall ſay in his Heart, <hi>My Lord delays his coming;</hi> and ſo put his Day afar off, to let Night again over you; You may remember what Sorrow and Heavineſs we endured when we were Children of the Night, and covered with thick Darkneſs, and what Joy came in the Morning of God's glorious Day, as it dawned in our Hearts; did not many then ſing for Joy of Heart, and experimentally could ſay, <hi>The ſinging of Birds was come?</hi> But the evil and ſloathful Servant that ſaith in his Heart,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34750:5"/>
               <hi>My Lord delays his coming,</hi> cannot ſing out of any ſence of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Joy in his Heart, and therefore frets and ſmites his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Servant, and eats and drinks with the Drunken, ſuch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Companions of the evil and ſloathful Servant, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights not to be a Companion to them that fear the Lord, and are diligent in his Work; nor will not ſay to the workers of Iniquity, <hi>Depart from me, I will keep the Commandments of my God;</hi> but rather joyns with the workers of Iniquity, and is one with them in breaking the Commands of God, and rebelling againſt him; and its juſt with the Lord to ſuffer Night to come over ſuch again, that have been called to ſerve the Lord in his Houſe, but are evil and ſloathful Servants; not good, not dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, nor watchful, but are found bad, negligent and unwatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and unſenſible of God's preſence, and the coming of the Lord, which draweth nigh: Oh! keep in the Spirit and Power of the Lord God, and that will preſerve you all fervent in love to him, and one another, and diligent in the Lord's work where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto you are all called with a holy calling, to watch &amp; war againſt the Devil; and whatſoever is of him, let it have no place in you, nor let not the Devil ever enter your Hearts any more, and if he do, not to dwell there, but feel you the Arm and Power of the Lord to caſt him out, &amp; keep him out, that he may never work in you any more, nor have any Lordſhip or Rule in you, or over you, then I am ſure you will be ready in Heart and Mind to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that which is good; and reſiſt the Devil, and all his badneſs which is ſo beloved of the World, and then you will be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to avoid every appearance of Evil, and will give no place to it, but will keep faithful to God over it, and then you will be made capable <hi>in the Spirit of Love, and a ſound Mind,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove ſuch as are light, vain, and of a looſe behaviour, and ſhun the Croſs of Chriſt; &amp; not indulge that Nature &amp; Spirit that keeps ſome high and unſubjected, and in diſobedience to the Lord God; and for this cauſe ſome are weak and ſick amongſt us, and ſome fallen aſleep; had they but taken up the daily Croſs, and kept therein, there would never have appeared that Self love, Weakneſs, Sickneſs and Sleepineſs, that is in ſome that are amongſt us, that would be accounted wiſe Virgins, and indeed have come long enough among us to have been found ſuch at this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34750:5"/>day, but are not, but are weak as in the time of their firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincement, and as if they had not waited upon the Lord with us; they ſo faint, and have ſo little ſtrength to ſtand in the day of Tryal, or hour of Temptation, that it appears their ſtrength is but ſmall. I ſay in the Lord, if they that now faint in the time of Adverſity, had waited upon the Lord in diligence and ſincerity of Heart, doubtleſs they would have had more ſtrength, and received more Power from God than they enjoy or feel, and would have grown more in the Grace and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God than they have done, and would not have been ſo ſick at their Stomachs as ſome are, that they cannot digeſt wholſom Food, but ſlight and diſ-eſteem it, whereby ſome Members ſuffer; and indeed it hurts the whole Body, when any of the Members thereof ſuffer, eſpecially as the Apoſtle ſaid then, <hi>when many were Weak and Sick amongſt them,</hi> and <hi>ſome fallen aſleep</hi> for want of ſubjecting themſelves to that Spirit and Power, which would give all ſtrength, if they kept in it, and preſerve all in God's ſaving health, and with a good Stomach to that which is good, and for Food, if they did wait for it, and keep in the Spirit and Power of the Lord God, this would rouze up and awaken all careleſs and ſleepy Virgins, that want Oyl in their Veſſels and Lamps, who have not their Lamps trimed, nor are ready when the Bridegroom comes; Beware ye ſleepy, fooliſh Virgins, leſt Mid-night Sleep come quite upon you, ſo that the Cry of the Bride-groom's coming be before you are prepared for him, or the door of entrance in with him be ſhut againſt you, or you prepared for his entertainment; the ſloathful Servant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing apt to delay the doing of his Duty to the Lord, imagins that the Lord delays his coming, then he doth that which he ſhould not do; and ſo cauſeth his Lord and Maſter, that is full of Mercy and Love, to be angry with him, and reward him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Deeds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> therefore love the Croſs of Chriſt, whereby you will learn to take up your daily Croſs, and follow your Captain Chriſt Jeſus, the Captain of our Salvation, that endured the Croſs, and deſpiſed the Shame, and was made perfect through Suffering; follow him in the Croſs, as you deſire to have the Crown; deſpiſe the Shame of the Croſs, and endure it, and do
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34750:6"/>not ſhun it, for you will not be as <hi>David,</hi> nor witneſs <hi>David</hi>'s Houſe to be as God's, if you ſhun the Croſs, nor will you grow ſtronger and ſtronger, as you ought, if you are troubled at the ſhame of it; you will never deny your ſelves much for Chriſt if you ſhun the Croſs, or be amazed at the daily taking of it up; whilſt 'tis ſo with any convinced of God's heavenly Truth, they will not ſhut out the world's Spirit, Words nor Actions, but will be luſting after the world's Words, vain Faſhions, Wayes, and not come out into a clear ſeperation from them, nor be capable to bear witneſs againſt the World, nor their Words, Wayes, vain Faſhions and Actions that are contrary to the Lord, and whereby his holy Spirit is vexed from day to day, ſuch amongſt us that will not croſs their own Wills, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled Tongues, to ſpeak <hi>Thou</hi> to any ſingle Perſon, high or low, but give way to a worldly and fleſhly Will, and fleſhly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, will not be willing to follow the Lord and his Servants, the Prophets and Apoſtles in their true Language, which was uſed by them that writ and gave forth the Scriptures, from <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis</hi> to <hi>Revelations;</hi> and can ſuch be now good? or is their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion good? who have been long convinced and come amongſt us, that have not a Bridle for their Tongues, nor do not know the Power of God's Truth, profeſſed by them, to tame their Tongues; Why are ſome in this eſtate, anciently convinced, but becauſe they would not ſubject their worldly corrupt Wills to God's holy Power, which would have made them willing ſo to do, and would have made them willing to have left all for Chriſt, and to have ſuffered the loſs of all things, though it had been never ſuch a Darling-beloved, for Chriſt's ſake.</p>
            <p>So let every one leave and forſake all which the Lord hath called you to forſake, whether it be <hi>Father, Mother, Wiſe, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Lands</hi> or <hi>Livings,</hi> and come to that whereby the laying down of a man's own Life may be made eaſie, which a Diſciple of Chriſt ought to do, when called of God thereunto: And as you all keep in the Croſs of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, you will be preſerved in a pure ſeperation from the whole World that lieth in Wickedneſs, and are Ungodly as the old World was, which God deſtroyed by Water; and you will be Preachers of Righteouſneſs (as righteous <hi>Noah</hi> was) by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34750:6"/>a righteous Life and Converſation, which will ſpeak more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, and have a louder cry in their Ears than <hi>Noah</hi>'s building the Ark had, although that had a ſpeaking in it, if the old World had not been dull of hearing, and cloſed their Eyes, they might have heard God's ſpeaking Voice, and have ſeen his Providence in it to preſerve <hi>Noah,</hi> and his Righteous Family; though they were but few in number, God ſaved them, and preſerved them in the Ark, which <hi>Noah</hi> was a building before the Flood came and drowned the Ungodly old World; and he will not ſpare the Ungodly World now, but till their Sins be full, and they ripe for a Deluge or Deſtruction, and then it will come upon them, and overtake them before they are aware thereof: and now many are uncircumciſed in Heart and Ear, and will not be warned, nor take notice of God's hand that is lifted againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friends,</hi> take heed of mixing with the wicked World, now have no fellowſhip with them, nor their works of Darkneſs, for as you are the Children of the Light, and of the Day, what fellowſhip can any of you have with Darkneſs, or the works of the whole World that lieth in Wickedneſs? or how can you touch with them in their corrupt Communication, Wayes or Worſhip, or any of their unclean and polluted things, but rather reprove and rebuke them that are found therein: And keep true and faithful to the Lord God, who called you out of the World, and ſeperated you from the Kindreds of the Earth, to ſtand for God, and to be living Witneſſes againſt the Devil and all his works; and you are called of God to ſtand with the Lamb, and his faithful followers, againſt the Devil, never more to joyn with the Devil, or take part with his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, ungodly Followers in their Sins and Treſpaſſes, nor in their Wrongs, Oppreſſion and Cruelty, nor contribute any ſtrength to them, ſtand clear, and in a pure and ſpiritual ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, from all that which God's holy Spirit and Light con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns and judgeth to be evil, and contrary to the Light, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and Grace of God; give not way to that, to ſave the world, or its Favour; temper not with the Snares nor Baits of this World, but in the hour of Temptation keep low, waiting upon the Lord God, who knows how to ſave &amp; deliver you, and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34750:7"/>to ſuccour you when you are tryed, and to preſerve you out of the power of your old Adverſary, or any of his Snares, Baits or Temptations, God hath by his Light let you ſee what you ought to chuſe, and what you ought to refuſe; chuſe the good, cleave to the good, whatever you may go through or ſuffer for ſo doing, chuſe Liſe, that you may live forever; and how ſew or many ſoever your dayes may be in this World, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the evil, and the wayes of Death and Deſtruction; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever hath not the mark of Truth upon it, as to Way, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or Religion, refuſe it, and enter into no Conſultation with the Devil, or his bad ſenſual Reaſoning, which he will fill them with, that deſire and conſult wayes to conform in this or the other thing relating to Faith, Religion and Worſhip, which never was, nor is of the Lord; and when the Wind bloweth high, Rain fall, and Sea rage and foam, then eſpecially look carefully and diligently to your ſtanding, and look to Chriſt Jeſus the everlaſting Rock, that is higher than you, and higher than the Heavens, and who is the author and finiſher of your Faith; all ſteadfaſtly look to him, truſt in him, fear him, and think upon his Name, and ſtill remember that the Lord God by a mighty Hand and Arm ſtretched forth, brought you out of <hi>Egypt</hi> ſpiritually: Do not forget that we were once Bonds-men in <hi>Egypt,</hi> nor how the Lord brought us forth, and the eminent Hand of the Lord that appeared in our deliverance and freedom from <hi>Egypt</hi>'s hard Task maſters; and the Lord did redeem us from the <hi>Heathen,</hi> and their <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> Words, Faſhions, Wayes and Worſhips, never to learn their Words, Wayes, Faſhions or Cuſtoms any more: And God called us out of <hi>Sodom</hi> ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, and to leave the filthy Communication and Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> which we were never to look back upon any more; truly 'tis very dangerous being in <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, where our Lord was crucified; who can expect any thing but Ruin and Deſtruction to be found amongſt them that now declare their Sin as <hi>Sodom?</hi> Therefore let none of you go into <hi>Egypt</hi> again for any help, or think to have relief there, go not down thither, nor look back towards <hi>Sodom,</hi> leſt you periſh, or be found worthy of the Wrath and Diſpleaſure of Almighty God, by reaſon of going back into <hi>Egypt</hi> again, and then any
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34750:7"/>of you ſhould be found in <hi>Sodom</hi> or <hi>Egypt</hi> ſpiritually; for if there be a deſire in any to go back, and they draw back, God's Soul ſhall have no pleaſure in them; and God will be diſpleaſed with you that luſt after <hi>Egypt,</hi> or the Fleſh-Pots there, or any thing you were called of God to leave and forſake, when you came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> notwithſtanding a Sea of Troubles, and many Hardſhips may appear, yet ſtill reſolve in the Power of the Lord to go forward, and with heavenly delight follow the Lord fully; and look ſtill to the Lord, and not at any Hardſhips or Difficulties that may appear in your Journey, nor at the length of it neither: O! let none of you ſay, that Food which God hath given you from Heaven is light Meat, for that evidently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaks murmuring at the Food which God gives, whereof you have eaten with us; If any ſhall be filled ſo with unbelief, to ſlight that, and deſire <hi>Egyptian</hi> Fleſh-Pots, and begin to value that again, which you vomited up as unſavoury, and not good Soul's Food, and return to it again, ſad will the latter end of ſuch be, whatever their beginning was: And if any of you ſhould forſake the Lord, his Fountain of living Waters, and dig to your ſelves broken Siſterns that will not hold the living Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then a terrible day of Wrath, and the great Diſpleaſure of the Lord will come upon you, and ſo you may become Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Diſpleaſure, which to avoid, wait upon the Lord low in his fear, when you come into the Aſſemblies of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and earneſtly deſire that this Heart of Unbelief, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſome in all Ages departed from God, and went backward, and not forward, may not be found in you, reſolving for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in the fear, awe and dread of the Lord God, to cleave to the Lord, and follow the Lord in the doing of that which is good, and to keep out of Diſobedience, Sin and Evil, while you abide in this world: Come not to the Meetings of the Saints, as if it were a thing indifferent whether you came or did ſtay at home, ſuch luke-warm Hearers and Profeſſors of the Truth amongſt us, God will ſpue out, that are neither cold nor hot, and yet cold enough towards that which is good, the day is at hand that will manifeſt every Birth, every Tree, and every Spirit really as it is, unto all who witneſs the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:34750:8"/>meaſure of the heavenly Birth, or are Trees of Righteouſneſs, and who are of a right Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> give not way to that, to pleaſe your ſelves, or to gratifie the Devil, or any corrupt Men or Women in the Spirit of this World, which would intice you, or draw you thereunto, that you might be enſnared, and then ſuch will but ſport themſelves, to ſee any of you ſpeak, act and walk after the courſe of this World, as ſuch as would draw you into evil, do; but be not you like unto them, nor learn any of their wayes, for the wayes of evil men lead from God, and from his pure and precious Life, which he hath made manifeſt, and brought you into in meaſure; ſo be the more circumſpect, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and watchful; watch you in all things, that you may pleaſe the Lord, and endure Hardſhip and Affliction with God's cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, choſen and faithful, when we are called thereunto, that as true and faithful Warriors in the Spirit and Power of God, we may all be kept together in one Spirit to the end: Oh! be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect every Son and Daughter, Servant and Hand-Maid, have your Eye in your Head; and if thy Eye be ſingle, the whole Body will be full of Light, which tends much to the ſafety and preſervation of the whole Body, and the faithful are the Body of Chriſt, and Members one of another, and muſt needs be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of each others ſuffering; can one Member ſuffer, and not the whole Body ſuffer with it? <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> keep to Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Head of his Body, the Church, which he hath purchaſed with his own Blood; ſtill mind the Head, and hold the Head, that you all may be kept living Members of his Body, purely knit together, and firmly united unto him, that you may be compleat in him, wanting nothing of that ſtate which you ought to be in, as to a growing into him who is the fulneſs that filleth all in all: In your Aſſemblies diligently wait to feel his preſence more and more, purely to refreſh and comfort you, whereby more and more you will have living experience how good and ſafe a thing it is for them that fear the Lord, to meet often together, to wait upon and ſerve the Lord, and anſwer his will and requiring therein, whatſoever men may require contrary of us herein, we are to obey God rather then man or
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34750:8"/>man's Edicts to the contrary, whereby many times Storms ariſe, and the Sea comes to be troubled. <hi>Friends,</hi> forget not how the Lord hath covered us and ſheltred us, when former Storms and Tempeſts have been, and the Rain hath fallen, yea, when the Enemy hath come as a Flood, and the Floods of the Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly broke forth upon us in the Dragon's rage, to deſtroy the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Birth, and that which was of God in us; how the Lord by his mighty Power, which is an unlimitted Power, brought Help Salvation and great Deliverance, even when all other Helps failed, and ſtood afar off: I hope many yet living do remember, with Joy of Heart, how the Lord cauſed the Winds and Sea to obey him, and divided the troubled Waters where the Whore then did ſit, and now ſitteth, which was <hi>Nations, Kindreds, Tongues</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> all which the <hi>Whore</hi> ſits upon; for <hi>Nations, Kindreds, Tongues</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> are all <hi>like Waters,</hi> rouling, tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling upon Heaps, and are troubled, there is no ſettlement up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, few knowing what they all, nor why they are tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſo upon Heaps; but notwithſtanding the Saints, who are the <hi>Lamb's followers</hi> muſt paſs through theſe waters, and through the fire alſo; the Lord will divide the waters to make way for his <hi>Iſrael</hi> in this day; and though <hi>Rahab</hi> and the <hi>Dragon</hi> ſtand up in the way of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> God will cut <hi>Rahab,</hi> and wound the great <hi>Dragon,</hi> and whatſoever would ſtand up in his way to hinder his Work, ſnall be confounded, and fall before him; for <hi>ſtrong i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord that judgeth the great Whore,</hi> and <hi>divideth the Waters thereon ſhe ſits,</hi> and <hi>who will give her Blood to drink,</hi> who hath long drunk the Blood of the Saints, and ſtill thirſts after more Blood to drink <hi>about Conformity in matters of Religion, and the worſhip of God,</hi> but the hour of her Judgments is come, her Paint is ſeen through, and her golden Cup full of Abomination is clearly diſcovered, 'tis in vain for the Kings of the Earth to think to ſupport or heal her; nay, ſhe is not willing to be healed, but thinks ſhe hath no need of any healing Medicine, and truly I know none for her (that is to be deſtroyed, and muſt certainly be deſtroyed) even that <hi>falſe Church, myſtery Babylon,</hi> the <hi>Mother of Harlots,</hi> which hath called her ſelf Chriſt's Spouſe, but hath the marks and attire of an Harlot. My <hi>dear Friends,</hi> as God hath called you out of her, <hi>not to partake of her Sins &amp; Abominations
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34750:9"/>any more,</hi> keep out of her, and ſtand clear of her Devices and and ſubtil Strategems ſhe doth now, or hereafter may make uſe of to draw ye from Chriſt Jeſus, and the Church that is in God, to a Houſe of Wood and Stone, which they that are in <hi>Babylon</hi> call a <hi>Church,</hi> and call to the Sons and Daughters of <hi>Sion</hi> to come to their Church, and receive the Sacrament, who are come to the true Church, which is in the only true God, and are living Members thereof, united to Chriſt Jeſus our Head and Husband, and we need no other Head or Husband, nor need not come to any Church, but that which Chriſt is the Head and Husband of, from whom we receive of his living Bread, and Wine of his Kingdom; and his holy things are given to us by the Spirit that comes from the Father and the Son; and you know <hi>Friends,</hi> that whereas Chriſt ſaid, a little before he went away as (to his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance in the Fleſh) <hi>he would ſend the Comforter</hi> to his Diſciples, which was <hi>the Spirit of Truth, to lead and guide them into all Truth,</hi> promiſing them, that the Spirit ſhould take off his, and ſhew it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, which as they then did receive it, we are made now cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Witneſſes of it: So need not go to a Houſe of Wood and Stone, called <hi>Church,</hi> and there ſit amongſt the corrupt, putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied company of diſeaſed <hi>miſorable Sinners,</hi> that are ſo much out of Health, that they have no whole part in them; what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort can a healed Soul, or a ſound mind have in coming or ſitting amongſt them? where one may ſooner come by an evil Diſeaſe, than ever be ſoundly cured of any inward Diſtemper or Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and you partaking of God's goodneſs, and his holy things at his Table, and having ſpiritual Fellowſhip and Communion with him, that is abundantly better than all the Bread and Wine which is outward, and will decay, given by impure Hands to ſuch as communicate with them (as many times it is admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred) without any Commiſſion from God; and yet that we muſt by theſe Church-men be forced to come amongſt them, and eat and drink unworthily with theſe unworthy Adminiſtrators and Receivers of that which they call the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> is certainly both Unchriſtian and Unreaſonable, and very Unchriſtian-like, as the Adminiſtrators and Receivers of it, who would now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel us to eat and drink with them, will one day know to their Wo, if they Repent not in time; and we may juſtly deny ſuch, as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34750:9"/>for their Bellies ſake, without any authority from God, preſume to take upon them in a rude unchriſtian manner, three times (with the ſame Mouth that they bleſs God and curſe Men) to admoniſh us: You that are taught of the Lord, and have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his Counſel and ſpiritual Admonition from him, have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of him to admoniſh one another, and know them that watch for the Soul, from them that watch and lay in wait for their Prey and diſhoneſt Gain, <hi>whoſe God is their Belly,</hi> and <hi>who glory in their ſhame,</hi> who hunt you into their Courts to ſleece you, and ſeed themſelves with the Fat, and cloath themſelves with the Wool, which they obtain by making you and yours their Prey, in ſpoiling of your Goods. But <hi>dear Friends,</hi> let none of theſe things (that are at preſent, or things to come) be able to move you from the peaceable Habitation in the Life and Power of God, to which you are come, and have been kept living Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of; fear not, neither be at all diſmayed; conſider whoſe the Earth is, and who hath Power to give it when and to whom he pleaſeth; for it is not the Devil's, nor his Servants; Man is but as a Tenant of it at the will of the Lord God, who hath given us that great gift, his Son, ſhall he not with him freely give us all things? And be patient and reſt quiet and contented, although you ſhould be <hi>fed with the Bread of Affliction, and Water of Affliction</hi> for a ſeaſon; and that ſhall not be, unleſs God ſee it convenient for us: let this ſtill comfort you, <hi>the beholding of your Teacher near you, that cannot be removed into a Corner;</hi> and feel God's cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which is everlaſting, that he made with <hi>David,</hi> in all things well ordered and ſure (ſaid <hi>David</hi>) although then God made it not to grow, he had a <hi>ſure Hope,</hi> and <hi>doubted</hi> not of the growth of it in God's time and appointed ſeaſon; <hi>And the Viſion was for an appointed time, and at the end it ſhall ſpeak,</hi> the Prophet ſaid; wait for it, it will ſurely come, and will not tarry. You <hi>tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated Followers of the Lamb,</hi> that are come to ſtand with the lamb upon Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> never regard the <hi>high looks</hi> nor <hi>threats</hi> of them of <hi>Babylon, Sodom</hi> or <hi>Egypt,</hi> although they may hate you, and caſt you out for his Name ſake, in whom you have believed, God will make them bluſh for ſhame for their <hi>high looks,</hi> for <hi>God will ſmite them</hi> that threaten your Ruin and Deſtruction, and their deſigns <hi>God will diſcover, and confound them,</hi> before they be put in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34750:10"/>execution as the Wicked deſire, <hi>whom the Moth ſhall eat as doth a Canker, and the Wind ſhall drive them away like Stubble,</hi> &amp; the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall ſee it, and rejoyce over <hi>Babylon,</hi> when her Merchants, and them that traded with her, <hi>ſhall howl and lament, for Widdow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, Sorrow and Deſtruction ſhall come upon her in one Hour;</hi> and 'tis greatly dangerous to buy any of the Merchandize of this great Whore and falſe Church, that would force to their Church, Religion and Worſhip, ſuch <hi>that believe it, cannot make them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or do their Souls any good:</hi> What Church but the <hi>falſe,</hi> will by <hi>Priſons</hi> and great <hi>Penalties,</hi> endeavour to make them come to their Church, that are not of their Church, nor Religion, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do believe that God ever required thoſe Forcers, to force any into their Church, nor require them, whom the <hi>Compellors</hi> ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to come amongſt them? Theſe methods will not do to convince Conſcientious Perſons of any differing Religion, to come to that Houſe of Wood and Stone.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>dear Friends,</hi> you may perceive the Beaſt would have all, ſmall and great to worſhip him; how doth he ſeek to compel People to worſhip him, and receive his Mark, either on their foreheads or in their hands? and the cry is, <hi>Who is like unto the Beaſt? and who is able to make war with him?</hi> And none will be able to deny his worſhip, and refuſe his mark, but the faithful tribulated Saints of the moſt High, that abide with <hi>Michael,</hi> our Prince of Peace, who will ſtand with and by the Children of his People, the ſealed Ones, that have his mark on their foreheads, and utterly reject the Mark of the Beaſt, and deny it, whatſoever they may ſuffer for ſo doing. So, beware of the Mark of the Beaſt, freely reject and deny the worſhipping of the Beaſt, and the receiving of his Antichriſtian Mark; for if any man worſhip the Beaſt, or receive his Mark on their forehads, or in their hands, they ſhall drink of the Wine of the Wrath of God, and be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and condemned of him, and the Cup of the Lords Fury ſhall be poured forth for them to drink, without any mixture of his mercy or favour. Therefore, you Children of Light, and of Gods day, who have known that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay ſo far to dawn in your hearts, as to have a diſcovery of the <hi>Whore, Beaſt, falſe Prophet</hi> and <hi>falſe Church,</hi> and have warred in the Lambs warfare, (againſt the Beaſt in any meaſure, and in the Light of the Lamb have ſeen and denyed the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34750:10"/>Whore and her golden Cup) ſtill maintain your War in the Lambs Spirit and Power, againſt the Beaſt, and let your hatred be againſt the Whore &amp; her Cup as much as ever; for the whore and her cup is no better now than when you firſt ſaw her, and began to hate her, and burn her fleſh with fire, and her cup is the very ſame now, however ſhe may guild it. I know God hath ſhewed, and will more manifeſt to you the My ſtery of the great Whore that ſits upon many Waters, Nations, Kindreds, Tongues and People, and he is willing to preſerve you, and will keep you from adhering to her, or the beaſt on which ſhe rides, and that carries her; if you will hearken ſtill unto the Lord, and obey him, he will defend you from the cruelty of the great red Dragon, Whore, Beaſt and falſe Prophet, and will take the Beaſt, and with him the falſe Prophet, and give them to the burning ſlame. <hi>He that hath an Ear to hear, let him hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And remember how freely the Lord hath made you to drink of the Waters of Life, and how that water hath been in you as a Well ſpringing up to Life eternal; and how can any of you that have known the waters of a full Cup, from God given unto you, (and to your great ſatisfaction have drunk thereof) return again to the foul and muddy Waters, that have no clearneſs nor life in them? Such as keep in the ſence of that Life, and Waters of it, which Chriſt hath given us, I know will never again meddle with the corrupt foul muddy Waters which the Whore and falſe Church gives to her Children; but the Bread and Water of Life, which you have fed upon, and drunk of at the Table of the Lord, the Children of the great Whore know not; and therefore their cry hath been, <hi>Come to the Church, receive the Sacrament;</hi> if you do, you muſt pay for it, and if you do not, you muſt pay the more, and be cited to appear at Courts, which they call <hi>Courts Spiritual;</hi> but how carnally they act in keeping of them, and in proceeding againſt them that for Conſcience ſake towards God cannot pertake with them, let all that fear God judge.</p>
            <p>Oh! <hi>dear Friends,</hi> fear not the Wrath of man, though his heart be lifted up never ſo much in manifeſt Oppreſſion, and threaten to act it upon you; but ſtill know you, and believe, that the remainder of mans wrath, God will reſtrain, and diſappoint the Wicked; caſt not away your Confidence, but wait patiently
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34750:11"/>upon God, and he will reſtrain the Wrath of the Wicked Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, that they will be confounded in their ungodly Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and not be able to effect their vile purpoſes: Depart not from the Faith which God hath given you, the Myſtery of which is held in a pure Conſcience; ſtand faſt in it, then I doubt not but ſuch will quit themſelves in this day, through the Lords aid and aſſiſtance, from all the Snares that now are, or hereafter may be laid to catch and hurt the innocent, and betray the ſimple. So in the peaceable, pure wiſdom and power of the Lord, keep over all the treacherous dealers, who ſet a trap to catch men, and who are full of deceit and flattery, and will ſpeak you fair ſometimes, as well as at other times ſhew their Teeth, ready to devour you, or eat you up; with the wiſdom and power of the Lord God, keep out of them and over them; for their delight is in Miſchief, to oppreſs a man and his houſe, but the Lord ſeeth and knoweth all the intents and purpoſes of the Wicked, with all their wicked works, and will reward them accordingly.</p>
            <p>Do you ſee Clouds to appear and ariſe? remember it is ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>That he cometh with the Clouds;</hi> and then ſhould be a time of great Trouble, and how it ſhould be a day of Darkneſs, and Clouds, and thick Darkneſs, and that covereth the Earth, and Nations; for ſo is the day of the Lord to the Wicked, its a day of gloomineſs and darkneſs, but not light: Now to behold Chriſt in the Clouds, how comfortable and glorious is it! but more glorious &amp; comfortable to ſee him expelling of them, and cauſing the ſhadows of Death and Darkneſs to vaniſh away, which they do, and muſt do, as the Son, Chriſt Jeſus, the Subſtance, comes into Peoples hearts, and is revealed in them. You that witneſs Chriſt ſo come, ſee him in the clouds, and how he breaks thorow the clouds, &amp; driveth all away, that he may cauſe his day to dawn more in clearneſs. And Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Behold, I come as a Thief in the night;</hi> bleſſed is he that watcheth and keepeth his garments, leſt he walk naked, &amp; men ſee his ſhame; it is not ſafe in a ſtorm for men to be naked, without their garments that ſhould cover them when diſtreſs cometh.</p>
            <p>And now, a ſtormy Wind bloweth, <hi>dear Friends,</hi> be ye all watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and clothed with the <hi>garments of Praiſe,</hi> which God promiſed to give his People, inſtead of the <hi>ſpirit of Heavineſs;</hi> and it will
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34750:11"/>be a great Wo upon all them that have not the Spirit of the Lord to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver them with in this preſent Storm, and when diſtreſs of Nations cometh, that are not, as good men and women, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Lords coming, whether at Mid-night, Cock-crow, or when ever it be; <hi>for the day and hour knoweth no man;</hi> and Chriſt ſaid, <hi>In an hour when you think not, the Son of Man cometh;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how are we all concerned to be always ready, and prepared for him, to ſerve, worſhip &amp; follow him whitherſoever he goeth? And Chriſt ſaid, <hi>When the Son of Man cometh, ſhall he find Faith on the Earth?</hi> ſignifying the great loſs and want of Faith, that ſhall be when he cometh, and what ſhipwrack will be made of Faith; notwithſtanding I doubt not but this day of Trouble will be of great uſe unto all who are honeſt in heart, and have believed with us, and provoke ſuch to examine themſelves, whether now they be in the Faith or not, and truly to ſearch their own hearts, and thorowly prove themſelves; and ſo no doubt but all the Sons and Daughters of <hi>Sion</hi> will come out of the Furnace more pure than Gold ſeven times tried in the ſire; &amp; truly a thorow ſearch, trial and examination will hurt neither the ſtrong in Chriſt, nor the weakeſt of the Flock; it will, doubtleſs, be of great benefit for all to examine themſelves whether they be in the faith or not; <hi>for he that ſtandeth, ſtandeth by Faith, and liveth by Faith, and pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God by Faith, and holdeth the Myſtery of it in a pure Conſcience; and worketh Righteouſneſs by Faith, and ſtops the Lyons Mouthes, and eſcapes the edge of the Sword by Faith; and out of weakneſs are made ſtrong through Faith, and valiant for the Truth, in warring againſt all that which works againſt the Truth, and is for untruth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Friends,</hi> to be rich in Faith, ſuch durably are made rich, and ſuch may be inſtrumental in the hand of the Lord to make others rich, although they be poor in this World; for it is the poor of this world (rich in Faith) that are <hi>Heirs</hi> of <hi>Gods Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So, you poor of the Flock, that honour God in your day, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with ſuch things as you have; nay, though you ſhould have leſs, and be made as poor as any are, do not repine nor murmur in your hearts againſt God; do not thou ſay in thy haſte, <hi>Why is my Lot and Portion of this World ſo little, and ſo hard?</hi> but mind thy being rich in Faith, and ſtill look unto Jeſus, the Author and Finiſher of thy Faith, that hath made thee rich in Faith, and thou
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34750:12"/>wilt be as well contented with ſuch things as thou haſt, as them who are out of the Faith, though they be never ſo much increaſed with Corn, Wine and Oyl, or have this world's Goods in never ſuch abundance; And if thou be'ſt poor and needy, conſider the poor, diſtreſſed and ſtript eſtate of Gods innocent Servant <hi>Job,</hi> and by what he was upheld and kept from ſinning againſt God; let the ſame Love to God be in thee, and the ſame uprightneſs and patience will preſerve thy goings aright, and keep thee from murmuring when thou wanteſt many things that others enjoy. Thou knoweſt that <hi>Dives</hi> was rich, but <hi>Lazarus</hi> was poor, and was deſirous of the crums that fell from the rich mans Table: <hi>Dives</hi> had his good things, but <hi>Lazarus</hi> his evil things in this world, a Beggar; the Rich man dyed, and the Beggar alſo; the Rich man was Wicked, and went into Hell, to be tormented in that Fire; but <hi>Lazarus</hi> was received into <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Boſom, and was bleſſed and comforted with faithful <hi>Abraham,</hi> who is called the Father of the faithful. And you that are poor in this world, conſider Chriſt Jeſus, who in the days of his fleſh had not whereon to lay his head, though the Foxes had holes, and the Birds of the Air their neſts; and your heavenly Father knoweth what you have need of, and will let you want no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of thing that he ſeeth good for you; be content that you are Heirs of Gods Kingdom, and that God hath promiſed you Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in Heaven; keep your Hearts to that, and priſe that above all earthly, cankering, or the ruſty Treaſure of this world, and it will go well with you forever and evermore.</p>
            <p>The Riches of this World, and all its Honour and Glory, that is uncertain, and takes to it ſelf Wings and flyes away; but we being rich in Faith and in good Works, that will abide and follow us, when we are gone hence, and ſhall be no more ſeen in this world; but the Riches of this world, and its Delights and Pleaſures will come to an end, &amp; now are flying away from many whoſe minds were lifted up, and who were puffed up in their minds with it. And the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Charge them that are Rich in this World, that they be not high-minded, nor truſt in uncertain Riches, but in the living God, who gave them all things richly to enjoy.</hi> And <hi>Job</hi> ſaid, <hi>Naked came I into this World, and naked ſhall I return again;</hi> and that <hi>the Lord gave, and took away, and could bleſs the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34750:12"/>Name of the Lord:</hi> He thus ſaid in his poor ſtript and diſtreſſed ſtate; and the Love, Faith and Patience of <hi>Job</hi> giveth true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedneſs now, and ſuch as have it caſt their care upon the Lord, and he takes care for them. And <hi>Friends,</hi> you that are rich in this World, keep your Minds out of it, or elſe it will become a ſnare to you; and your Table may become a ſnare, if you keep not low &amp; ſober in the uſe of theſe good things that you enjoy in this world; &amp; although God gives you them for your welfare, yet they may become a trap; and if when they encreaſe you let your hearts after them, and ſet your hearts on them, undoubtedly they will prove ſo to you, as well as other People. Therefore keep low, and take heed to your ſelves, that the Earth get not over you again to oppreſs and burthen that Seed of God in any of you; for then you will begin to walk heavily on, and pull back your Shoulder from many good works and ſervices that you might do for God in your day, and will neglect the doing of them; and if (when Riches encreaſe) you ſet your hearts on it, it will ſteal away the hearts of ſuch from the Lord, then what availeth any thing of a drawing near to God with the Tongue, or Lips, or any Bodily exerciſe, that you may be exerciſed in; For in this ſtate Pride and vain Glory creeps in, and a deſire after the Glory of the World, and a love to it, and to deck themſelves very unbecoming Truth profeſſed and talked of by them, and to get into the vain Faſhions and Modes of the world; becauſe they have gotten more of it than others, they may think that they may get into fine Apparel, and needleſs things the world uſeth to wear; and ſo much of that which is needleſs and ſuperfluous is worn by ſome, eſpecially that are young, that it is a ſhame their Parents, that have the government of them, ſhould ſuffer them in it.</p>
            <p>So <hi>dear Friends,</hi> who are Parents of Children, wait diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the Lord in his Light, that with his Light you may ſee betimes into the Natures, Inclinations and Diſpoſitions of your Children, and have a watchful and good Eye over them, and their Inclinations; and if you ſee they are inclinable to that which is good, cheriſh that in them, if it be never ſo little, ſtrengthen it, that more may ariſe in them, and they may more come to ſee and taſte with you how good and gracious the Lord is; and be good Examples to them in words and actions, that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34750:13"/>they may hear gracious words from you, and behold your good Converſation coupled with fear, fear to offend the Lord, and fear to do any thing againſt his glorious Truth, and then you will ſhine as Lights among them and your whole Families, and amongſt all the Children of men: But if you ſee your Children incline towards that which is evil, to Pride, vain Faſhions of the World, or that they delight in the company of the Wicked, and in Sports, and that they evilly ſpend their time; without delay, check and ſharply reprove them for it, and endeavour as much as in you lies, to ſtop and reſtrain them there-from; and ſtubbornneſs, high-mindedneſs and all manner of Evil, labour in the love and wiſdom of God to break them from, and keep down in them. If any ſay, <hi>What can I do? God muſt do all.</hi> I fear ſome amongſt you have omitted your Duty on your part, to do as <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Parents, under that pretence of God's doing all, and therefore do not train up your Children in the way of God, Truth and Life as you ought to do: But ſuffer them not to learn the corrupt wayes of evil Men and Women, and to chuſe their wayes; 'tis true, <hi>God worketh all our Works in us and for us;</hi> but as he worketh immediately by his Spirit and Power in our hearts, he alſo worketh by Inſtruments; and you in the wiſdom and ſpirit of God are, or may become fit Inſtruments for God to work on your Children and Families by, and to reclaim your Children and Families from Vice and Wickedneſs, which you may ſee them incline unto; If the believing Husband may ſave his Wife, and the believing Wife her Husband, that believeth not, then why may not you, as believing Parents, ſave your Children, duly watching over them for good, believing in God for them, and doing your duty to them carefully, and in God's heavenly wiſdom? And why may not you, your Children and Families be thus ſanctified and ſaved from the Abominations of the times, and the Evil of the World, while you and they are in it? If wholly you diſcharge your duty and truſt, as Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents or Maſters of Families; and then if your Children or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, notwithſtanding remain wicked, you will be clear, and their Blood will come upon themſelves, or at their Doors. I doubt not but there are many Parents have a Godly care over their Children, and as Maſters, and Miſtreſſes or Dames have
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34750:13"/>a Chriſtian care over their Servants and whole Family, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them in the way of Righteouſneſs, and that reprove and correct their Children, and their Servants, when they ſee them do that which is evil. But this is written in the love of God, as a caution to and reflection upon all who are negligent and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs amongſt us in this reſpect, that all may come into a care of God's glory, and of their Children and Servants, that as much as in you lies, you endeavour to reclaim, and reſtrain them from Sin and Evil, and train them up in that which is good, that you all may be able to give account to God with Joy, when by him you may be called to an account how you have governed and ruled your Families, trained up your Children, counſelled and adviſed your Servants, and what Examples you have been to your Families, whom God gave you the rule and government of here, a few dayes in this World. And you believing Husbands, who have Wives that believe not, love your Wives, and be very careful how you ſpeak and act towards them, that no blemiſh may come upon the Truth by any unadviſed words to your Wives, neither any unſeemly carriages or behaviour, that if poſſible, you may gain your Wives, that believe not, to the Lord, and belief of his precious Truth. And you Wives, that have Husbands that believe not, ſpeak and do likewiſe the ſame to them, that you all may be found Holy and Unblamable in the day of God, that the unbelieving Wife may be ſanctified by her believing Husband, and the unbelieving Husband by his belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Wife, loving and cheriſhing the good in them that believe not, whether Husband or Wife; but keeping clear of that which is Evil, never joyn with that which is Evil, for thereby you will not only hurt and darken your ſelves, but alſo harm your Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſtrengthen them the more in that which is evil, and contrary to God, and make your Lives more uncomfortable. And all <hi>Husbands</hi> and <hi>Wives</hi> in general, live in Love, in the love of God, out of a pure Heart loving and cheriſhing one another, ſubmitting your Hearts to God and his counſel in one another, as the Lord by his Spirit may move in any of your Hearts, ſo to counſel and adviſe each other therein, that you may be made to each other meet helps in the Truth, and helps in him to advance that in your Families, or in helps in Government in the Church
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34750:14"/>of God. And <hi>Children,</hi> be ſubject, and in obedience to your Parents in the Lord, that you may pleaſe the Lord; for the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born and diſobedient diſpleaſe the Lord, and come ſhort of the Bleſſing of the Lord, whilſt ſo, I mean his Bleſſing in heavenly things, and often in this world and its things, they are not bleſſed to them, nor do not enjoy them in the bleſſing of God: Take heed Children, diſobedience to Parents is a great evil, to diſobey them and their Commands, being that which is good; Let none be high, or ſet not your ſelves againſt ſuch Commands, if you do, God will puniſh you for it, and kindle his wrath againſt you; if your Parents command you to keep out of evil Company, and out of bad Words and Actions, obey them, or elſe it will be ill with you. Parents care being over you for good, will you grieve them, by rewarding them evil for good, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion towards them, inſtead of eſteem, honour and duty, which you owe to them, even ſo much as you can ſcarce do it enough? therefore diligently mind your Parents commands in the Truth, to obſerve and do them. And all you <hi>Servants,</hi> that are convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of and own God's Truth, let God's fear be before your Eyes, and let his Truth guide and order you, and keep you, that you may be inabled by the Lord to diſcharge your duty in the place of a Servant, every one of you, not as Eye Servants, or ſloathful and careleſs in your Maſters buſineſs, knowing you muſt give an account to God for any evil in this reſpect done by you; and you ought to do, in all matters belonging to your place, as what you did and were concerned in, were your own; and you ought to perform buſineſs in your Maſters abſence, as if pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and ſhun all Couſining and Defrands, and ſeek your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters profit, and be obedient unto them, and ſubject to them in all their lawful and juſt Commands, that the bleſſing of God, and the good pleaſure of your Maſters you may obtain; do not deſpiſe or ſlight the commands of them, becauſe they are Godly, or may bear more with you, &amp; allow you more <hi>juſt Liberty</hi> than the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed will do, for that would prove Wickedneſs in you, and incur their diſpleaſure, which you may avoid if you be wiſe; and rightly conſider your place and ſtation, and do not ſtrive unlawfully to get out of it; And take you heed what Words you uſe, and what Actions you do amongſt your Maſters Children; for your evil
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34750:14"/>example, doubtleſs, may do much hurt to Children, who many times are more inclinable to the bad, than that which is good, you being frequent with them, by your bad Words and Actions, may give great ſtrength unto; incourage no corrupt Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, nor provoke them to Laughter, fooliſh Jeſting, nor any unſeemly behaviour, to ſtir up the wrong part, that you and your Maſters Children ought to check and keep down in each other <hi>by the Grace of God,</hi> which you all being taught by, will make them good Children, and you good Servants, and then the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Lord will reſt upon you, whether Servants, or made free, and whether ſingle, or in a married condition, wherein are the greateſt Snares, Troubles and Incumbrances. And you that are ſingle, be not over haſty to force your ſelves from that ſtate, to change your conditions, (I ſpeak this both to Friends, Children and Servants) wait the Lord's due time, and wait low in his fear in it, <hi>that you may be taught of the Lord,</hi> what to do, and not Sin againſt God in changing your conditions; and take heed of being unequally yoked, or marrying with the World, although they may be civiliz'd, and have eſtabliſhed to themſelves a Righteouſneſs, which is not the Righteouſneſs of God, which if you be not aware of, may beguile your Simplicity, and anger the Lord God, and grieve your Parents that waited for, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected better things from you; ſo your Marriage will not be honourable, nor you and them (you make thus choice of) be joyned together in Marriage by the Lord: Therefore take heed of the World and the World's Spirit, which leads from God; for that will lead you to love the world, and to have an Eye out to the Riches of it in your choice, and the Beauty of their Daughters, that have not believed nor received the Truth: You Young Men will look out after, and may be you ſee ſome elder than you drawn by the ſpirit of this world into the ſame Practices, and you may ſtrengthen your ſelves in that, which God never juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you nor them in, but you are both condemned for, when you come to the witneſs of God, and hearken to the witneſs of God in your own Conſciences, that never conſents to any unequal yoking, nor any thing elſe that is done contrary to God, by any amongſt us, whether they be Young or Old, Rich or Poor, Married or Unmarried, God doth not juſtifie, but he condemns
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34750:15"/>all bad Marriages, and other things, now as much, nay, more then in the times of Ignorance; although he diſallowed them ever ſince the beginning of this World, and forewarned the Holy Seed not to mingle themſelves in Marriage with the <hi>Heathen,</hi> and commanded them to keep themſelves Pure, and to be Holy, with this caution, <hi>I the Lord your God am a Holy God;</hi> but they not regarding the command of the Lord, and taking to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Wives of all ſorts, thereat God was grieved, <hi>And it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented the Lord that he had made Man,</hi> when he ſaw the provoking of his Sons and Daughters, and he ſaid, <hi>I will cut off Man and Beaſt from the Earth.</hi> So, all you Unmarried, whether Young or Elder, that are convinced of God's Truth, and come amongſt us, look to the Lord in your proceedings in Marriage, wait low and enquire of the Lord firſt, whether it will ſtand with his honourable Truth, and be an honourable Marriage, that you have a mind to effect and bring to paſs, yea or nay; and if in anſwer from God, after patient waiting upon the Lord in it, you find that it will be to the honour of the Lord, and with the conſent of your Parents, go on, and the Lord will be with you, and will direct, guide and bleſs you in your undertaking, which is of very great weight; but if after a deliberate waiting upon God, you find not the Lord with you in your purpoſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, but that his Hand is againſt you and your purpoſe, then ſtay and give it up, and be not diſcontented, and haſtily carry on the matter in your own wills; nor let not your fond, fooliſh Affections ſway you ſo, that you may become Captives to them, or the Will and Luſts of the Fleſh; for then God's ſafe counſel will be hid from you, and you will run on in your own Wills averſe and oppoſite to the will of the Lord in that weighty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, whereby ſome diſhonour the Lord, defile their Bed, grieve and make ſad their Parents, or them concerned, as left in truſt with them, and endanger their own Ruin, both as to Soul and Body. So <hi>dear Friends,</hi> whether Young Men or Maidens, or more Aged, that may be concerned in this weighty matter of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, conſider theſe things, do nothing againſt the Truth, but look to the God of Truth, give up your ſelves to be at the Lord's diſpoſe and ordering, and he by his heavenly Wiſdom will preſerve you out of the Spirit of this world, and out of all the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34750:15"/>Wayes, Works and Snares of it. And you Parents of Children, give no encouragement or ſtrength to your Sons or Daughters (that are owned by us, or in the profeſſion of Truth with us) to Marry with the worlds People Sons or Daughters; keep your ſelves clear of ſuch mingling and Marriages, that are out of the Truth, which you cannot, nor your Children, expect comfort or Gods bleſſing in; let no Earthly end what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever prevail with any of you, to connive at, or encourage ſuch things in your Children; for if ſo, thereby will the worlds Spirit creep into you, as well as it hath done your Children that ſo proceed, and may darken God's counſel from both you and your Children, and hinder Gods bleſſings from your Familes, and let in the curſe amongſt you, and bring his diſpleaſure upon you and yours, and that is a woful thing. <hi>God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty lead, direct and guide you all in the things that concern your everlaſting Peace, which you are come to know and underſtanding; but the Wicked of the World know them not; and ſo in the day of the Lord you will be more inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, (acting againſt Knowledge) than ſuch will be that have not known thoſe things:</hi> So be ye all diligent and watchful, that you may be kept out of the World, and the Evil thereof, and <hi>keep God's holy Will and Commands all the days of your abiding in the World.</hi> And you <hi>Maſters, Miſtreſſes</hi> or <hi>Dames,</hi> behave your ſelves in the fear, awe and dread of the Lord in your reſpective Families towards your Servants, inſtruct and inform them, as God your Maſter in Heaven, by waiting upon him, will give you Wiſdom to do it, which Wiſdom will direct you how to ſpeak and act towards them, as ſuch that know they have a Maſter in Heaven, even ſo carry and behave your ſelves in your duty &amp; places to your Servants, forbearing threatning in any words you ſay to them, that whether your Servants believe, or be ſuch as believe not, you may by your good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication and Converſation reach the good, and anſwer Gods witneſs in them, and to put no ſtumbling blocks in their way, whereby to cauſe them to ſtumble, by <hi>haſty, raſh, unadviſed Words, that ſavour not of God, nor cometh of him that called you;</hi> you being kept in the fear and dread of your Maſter in Heaven, will have true and peaceable wiſdom given you, to carry your ſelves in your Families; ſo that the Truth will not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached, nor its way ſpoken evil of juſtly by your occaſion, and that greatly tends to the honour of the God of Truth, and increaſe his <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>counſel</hi> to order your own Houſhold or Family well, &amp; will bring ableſſing upon them. <hi>And I could not be clear in the writing of this Epiſtle to you, but to put you in mind of theſe things that are good to be known and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in every Family, which had I not ſeen a neglect of in ſome, there would have been no need of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>My dear Friends,</hi> that have tranſported, or may tranſport your ſelves or Families beyond the Seas, out of your Native Country, conſider
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34750:16"/>and throughly weigh your aims and ends therein, that they be ſuch as you may expect God's bleſſing in, and without ſeeking great things to your ſelves, or ſet your Neſts on high, leſt you fail in your expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and bring much Sorrow, Trouble and Exerciſe upon your ſelves and Families; from the richeſt to the pooreſt of you, ſeek Gods honour, and keep in his Counſel; wait low that you may enjoy Gods counſel, &amp; ſtand in it where-ever you are; for that is certain and ſafe, and will direct you certainly and ſafely, if you wait to be ordered and guided by it; and that as you keep in it, will bring a bleſſing to all the Countries where-ever you may be diſperſed, and bleſs your Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings where you Plant &amp; ſettle your ſelves; but whether you who are gone already, or ſuch as intend to go out of the Land, follow not your own wills, or fond weak affections in going into forreign Countries, or becauſe this or the other Perſon goeth, and may have a ſhare in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there; conſider, it is a weighty thing for one Perſon to remove out of his Country afar off, and his way clearly he ſees not, perhaps neither; and if ſo, its not only a weighty, but a dangerous matter to remove a whole Family for favour and affection; and affection not well governed may lead a man or woman far into things they have not a right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, nor clear ſight in, whereby ſome miſs their way in their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, which brings trouble, vexation of Mind, and diſcontents; not that I have any thing againſt any Perſon or Family going to ſettle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or Families, or to plant in any Country, that go in clearneſs, as to God, and ſingly mind his Honour and Glory more than any thing elſe beſides, that is viſible; for I know the Light of Gods countenance will bleſſedly ſhine upon ſuch where-ever they are; and they will not go in their own Wills, nor be ſwayed by fooliſh Affections to run into things, or do things haſtily, nor will or run in a heady mind in their underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, but will patiently wait upon the Lord, not only to know the mind and will of the Lord, but faithfully give up to do it, whether here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or any other Country; and ſuch dare not remove themſelves nor Families, but as they feel the Lord to countenance them in it, or have real &amp; true freedom in the clear Truth of God, which leads us out of, &amp; car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries over all worldly aims and ends, and ſeeking, giving or receiving any earthly Honour which is judged of the Lord God, and gratifieth only that worldly part and ſpirit that leads into it. And <hi>Friends,</hi> all of you, be ſure you neither had nor have in your hearts any ſecret reſerve (to ſave that which ought to be freely given up) in your <hi>tranſporting</hi> your ſelves; for where-ever that is, it ariſeth from Unbelief and carnal Reaſoning: And if there be any of you that have left the Land, or ſhall hereafter leave it, that ſhall do it to ſave liberty, eſtate or life (which I doubt not but you might have <hi>temptations</hi> to in your undertakings) certainly that will not be well; you may be in danger and jeapordy there, as well as we here:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34750:16"/>And by any particulars giving way to that here or there; they will thereby but render themſelves leſs capable to bear or keep up their Teſtimony for the Lord as all ought to do. Truly my hearts deſire and Prayer to <hi>God</hi> for you is, <hi>That you may be ſaved out of the many Snares and Dangers that may attend you there, as well as we your Friends and Brethren here left behind you; and that you with us may be kept forever to God, that we all may anſwer the Witneſs of God in all People, Nations, and of what Tongue ſoever;</hi> and it will be ſo, we keeping in Gods fear and wiſdom, and never departing from him or his counſel; hereby ſhall many Nations be converted to God, from their Idolatrous Ways and Practices. And come out of all what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is Evil and contrary to the Lord God, and ſo <hi>Friends</hi> will you with us, and we together with you in one Spirit of Love, Life and Power be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved out of the many Snares and Temptations to ſuch things as would diſhonour God, grieve his Spirit one in another, or be any occaſion of ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to them that will watch ſtrictly over both us &amp; you, that in all things we may ſo behave our ſelves, that the holy Name of the Lord, known and profeſſed by us, may never be reproached or blaſphemed by any of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries. Walk wiſely, and behave your ſelves in tenderneſs and lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mind towards the <hi>Indians</hi> or others, whom you may have occaſion to deal with, do juſtly, as you would they ſhould do unto you; and ceaſe from Anger and Wrath in converſing with them, that you may anſwer the juſt Principle of God in People of all Nations, which you may be concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with, that we may hear of your welfare and ſtedfaſtneſs in Chriſt Jeſus, that the Lord may be with you, and bleſs your Undertakings, is ſincerely the deſire of my Soul. And <hi>my dear Friends,</hi> in general, that love and fear the Lord, whatſoever things are good, pure, honeſt, that are of a <hi>good Report,</hi> or which have any virtue in them, think of &amp; heartily put in practice, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being offended at the leaſt thing or things that really are of God, and which he appears in, and bleſſeth his People in the Practice of. Oh! be of one accord and one mind therein; avoid all corrupt Reaſoning and needleſs Queſtions about ſuch things, as becometh Saints; and avoid all Evil Speakers, Whiſperers, Back-biters and Tale-bearers, who thereby would cool Brotherly Love, or make Diſcord, &amp; divide the Body of Chriſt Member from Member, to lay waſte Gods Heritage, and trample upon his pleaſant portion: In the fear and wiſdom of God keep, that you may be made capable Inſtruments to ſtop ſuch evil Inſtruments, and whatſoever is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad, impure, diſhoneſt, and of a bad Report; And in the Life of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and pure Judgment thereof, ſtand up for God as faithful Witneſſes, againſt that which would defile and work Abomination, when and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it would enter to hurt and ſpoil the Vines; for our Vines have tender Grapes, and the Lord of the Vineyard looks for Grapes from his Vineyard, but will be diſpleaſed with ſower Grapes, whoſoever bringeth them forth: And ſhut out all <hi>ſelf-Intereſt,</hi> &amp; that which would lead you to <hi>reſpect Perſons</hi> in Judgment, that nothing which is Evil may eſcape Judgment within in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34750:17"/>the particular, nor in ſuch amongſt us that do profeſs the Truth of God, whoever they be, rich or poor; and that the Righteous may be juſtified in Judgment, that an equal hand of true Judgment and Juſtice may ſtill be born, and flow forth towards all of the Houſhould of Faith, without reſpect to Perſons. <hi>God Almighty be with you all, and keep you in your ſtrong Tower of ſafety the name &amp; power of the Lord, now the winds blow hard, and the ſea ſwells; if any of you go out of the name of the Lord, into which you are gathered, and ſeek to ſave your ſelves without the Lord and his counſel, you cannot be ſafe, what courſe beſide ſoever you take: Therefore keep with the Lord in his name, light &amp; life, &amp; he will be with you to ſave &amp; deliver you out of the hands of all your Enemies, but do not preſcribe the Lord a way, how to work deliverance or bring ſalvation, leave that to him that it belongs unto, the time and manner of his ſaving, and making bare and ſtretching forth of his hand; but ſtand faſt in believing, be ſtill, and know continually, that God is God, and by Faith in his power you will ſee ſuch things brought to paſs as your Eyes yet never beheld done by Gods almighty Power. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt your ſelves ſtill peaceable, and quietly wait upon the Lord, who for the cry of the oppreſſed will ariſe, and his Arm will put on ſtrength; he will help the poor and needy, and will have mercy upon</hi> Zion, <hi>and favour his People who eye him, and coſt not away their confidence which you have had in his Power, and Gods everlaſting Covenant of Light, Life and Power feel made with you, even the ſure Mercies of</hi> David, <hi>and the bright and morning Sear to direct you, and guide you in all your ways, that none of you may err or go aſtray any more. And remember Gods Covenant and Promiſe, which is ſure, that he made with</hi> David <hi>and his ſeed, which greatly comforted</hi> David <hi>in his afflictions and troubles, that his Houſe was not with God, as it ought to have been; be thought upon Gods everlasting Covenant, he regarded that, and believed God would perform it in a time when be made it not to grow; and God ſaid,</hi> As my Covenant is wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the day and night, that there ſhall be day and night in their proper ſeaſons ſo is my Covenant with <hi>David</hi> and with his ſeed forever; &amp; <hi>David</hi> ſhall not want a man to ſit upon his Throne from henceforth &amp; forever. <hi>And the Lord ſaid,</hi> If I break my Covenant with the day and the night, that there ſhall not be day &amp; night, then will I break my Covenant with <hi>David. But we ſee God continues his Covenant with the day &amp; night, in their ſeaſon, as in his eternal wiſdom &amp; counſel be appointed in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, &amp; ſet all thing in order which he had made, &amp; the day &amp; night ever ſince, according to Gods Covenant hath remained, and kept their order even ſo God made his Covenant with</hi> David <hi>and his Seed.</hi> Therefore <hi>dear Friends,</hi> feel that you are all of the Seed and Off-ſpring of <hi>David,</hi> the bright and morning Star, and feel and be ſenſible of his ſure Mercies and Covenant with you, and extended towards you continually; and having received ſuch Mercies and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Promiſes, faint not, whatever may become of your outward Man or Eſtates in this world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> freel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> give up all to the Lord, from whom you have obtained many favours and peculiar deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances, when you were in great ſtraits, and have been ſorely beſet with the Enemy within and without, how did the Lord then appear to ſtand by you, and ſtrengthen you, when you had no other helper, nor looked for Salvation or ſtrength in the day of trouble, from any other certainly then was Gods time to appear, who then did confound your Foes, and ſtop and drive back the Powers of Darkneſs, that with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ood the Lords work, by his Power in you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd which he hath alſo begun in the Nations of the Earth, which he will carry on and proſper for his Names ſake and Covenants ſake, which in all things is well ordered and ſure, in which God Almighty keep you and eſtabliſh you all for evermore.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend &amp; Brother who forever deſires to be found one with the faithful in every good word and work <hi>JAMES PARKE</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Alton</hi> in <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he latter end of the 11th Mon. 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
